<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Oscar Moreno - iOS Developer </title><description>Articles about Swift and Apple development</description><link>http://oscarmoreno.com</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 5 Jan 2023 23:34:09 +0100</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Thu, 5 Jan 2023 23:34:09 +0100</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="http://oscarmoreno.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">http://oscarmoreno.com/blog/my-new-first-post</guid><title>My (new) first post</title><description>Who I am and why I have relaunch my blog</description><link>http://oscarmoreno.com/blog/my-new-first-post</link><pubDate>Sun, 2 Jan 2022 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi! I am very happy today, because I have refactored my blog 😉</p><p>This is not my first experience writing in my blog but, 2022 was a year with changes and new challenges in my working life so, I decided restart my blog to align it with what I am doing day by day.</p><p>For this reason, this is my first post, but only in this new version of my blog.</p><h2>About me</h2><p>If I have to talk about me in a sentence, I like to say that I am a passionate about programming and tech world.</p><p>Nowadays, I work as iOS Developer at <a href="http://www.hiberus.com">Hiberus</a>, a global consultancy company founded in Spain, but growing quickly and opening new offices in places such as Berlín, London, México DF or Miami.</p><p>But, my work experience have been mainly focused in IT. Besides programming, I have previous experience working as QA or DevOps engineer.</p><p>Recently, because I'm a enthusiastic user of Apple products, I decided to learn Swift, and specialize in their ecosystem development. Not only for iOS devices, but for MacOS or the rest of Apple operating systems.</p><h3>My personal life</h3><p>I was born in Valencia (Spain), where I live, at 80’s, the age of Spectrum, Atari and the first Sega's or Nintendo videoconsoles. So, I grow up and enjoyed play videogames with my Sega Megadrive, watch cartoons as He-man, Dragon Ball or Captain Tsubasa.</p><p>I'm the proud father of Lucas 👶🏻, my 2 years son that became the home CEO, and the proud husband of Lorena, the best life companion that I could have. A wonderfull woman, with a special power to treat with the childhood (And with me 😅)</p><p>Nowadays, I spend my non-working hours with my family or my hobbies, such as: enjoying TV Series, playing chess or watching Formula 1 races.</p><h2>Why I write in this blog</h2><h3>Knowledge</h3><p>The first reason (and the most important) is for learning. I think that there are 3 levels of knowledge: - 1st: When someone teach you something, or you learn it watching a video or reading a book - 2nd: When you are able to do what you have learned - 3rd: When you are able to teach someone what you know.</p><p>And, for this reason, write in a blog help me to learn teaching others.</p><h3>To help</h3><p>The second one, is helping others what today I love: programming. I think that everybody’s like help others, and also, this my way to extend the help that I receive from others.</p><h3>Express my opinion</h3><p>Another reason is, as iOS Developer, I need to have a deep understand about the Apple ecosystem so, this will be a place to organize my thoughts about the news, products, events as WWDC… but ever focused in coding</p><h3>Practice english</h3><p>And the last reason, (but no less important), practice to write tech documentation in English. My native language is Spanish, but globalization and remote working has opened a lot of opportunities. And English is today the key language for learn and work.<br><br>---</p><p>If you wanna know more about me, feel free to check my social media links (see the footer)</p><p>So, I hope you enjoy my posts! 🙂</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>